<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<section>
  <title>The number <m>e</m></title>
  <!-- \marginpar{\centering\resizebox{\marginparwidth/2}{!}{<m>e</m>}} -->
  <subsection>
    <title>Continuously compounded interest and the number <m>e</m></title>
    <author>Simonds/Hughes</author>
    <date>  April 2011</date>
    <p>
      Congratulations, you've just won the grand prize of one dollar in the 
      giga-millions Genuine Wheel of Fortune lottery game.  
      One dollar doesn't sound like much of a grand prize, but here's the 
      thing<em-dash/>you can deposit that dollar into a savings account that earns 
      interest at a rate of <quantity><mag>100</mag><unit base="percent"/></quantity> per year!  So after one year your prize 
      will have grown to <dollar/>2, after two years it will have grown to <dollar/>4, wait 
      a minute<ellipsis/>even after 10 years it has only grown to <dollar/>1024.  But 
      you know how these increasing exponential functions work; once they 
      get going, they really take off.  If you can manage to hold off your 
      withdrawal for twenty years you'll reap a little over a million dollars and 
      wait just five more years after that and you'll take home over 
      thirty-three million dollars!
    </p>
    <p>
      All of those figures are based upon the assumption that the 
      interest is compounded only once a year<em-dash/>that's where the wheel 
      comes in.  You spin the wheel to see the way in which the interest 
      will be compounded.  <xref ref="exp-tab-wheelfortune"/> shows the amount that will 
      be in your account at the end of year one if the interest is compounded 
      yearly, monthly, weekly, daily, every hour, every minute, and every second.  
      Make sure that you see the connection between the expression <m>\left( 1+\frac{1}{n} \right)^n</m>
      and the compound interest formula as it applies to this application.
    </p>
    <table style="margin" xml:id="exp-tab-wheelfortune">
      <caption/>
      <tabular>
        <col halign="."/>
        <col halign="."/>
        <thead>
          <row><cell><m>n</m></cell>  <cell><m>\displaystyle\left( 1+\frac{1}{n} \right)^n</m></cell></row>
      </thead>
      <row><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row>
      <row><cell>12</cell><cell>2.61303529</cell></row>
      <row><cell>52</cell><cell>2.69259695</cell></row>
      <row><cell>365</cell><cell>2.71456748</cell></row>
      <row><cell>8760</cell><cell>2.71812669</cell></row>
      <row><cell>525600</cell><cell>2.71827922</cell></row>
      <row><cell>31536000</cell><cell>2.71828247</cell></row>
      <tfoot/>
    </tabular>
  </table>
  <p>
            We can see that through the fifth digit after the decimal point the 
            amount in your account will be the same whether the compounding is 
            done by the minute or by the second.  If we were to continue increasing 
            the number of times we compound, we would find that the digits start to 
            get fixed farther and farther to the right of the decimal point.  
            However, no matter how many times we compound, if we look far enough to 
            the right of the decimal point the digits will be different if 
            the interest is compounded just one additional time. 
            That is to say
            <me>
            \lim_{n\to\infty}\left( 1+\frac{1}{n} \right)^{n}
            </me>
            is an irrational number (a number that in decimal form never terminates 
            and never forms a forever-repeating pattern).  
</p>
<p>
            It turns out that this very same irrational number pops up in a wide 
            variety of applications, and as such it is worthy of a name.  The 
            number is called Euler's number and is symbolized by the letter <m>e</m>.  
            If we let the number of times the interest is compounded increase without 
            bound, we say that interest is being compounded continuously.  In our 
            lottery game, if the interest is compounded continuously, then the amount 
            that would be in your giga-millions account at the end of year one 
            would be <m>e</m> dollars where <m>e\approx 2.71828</m>.
</p>
</subsection>
        </section>
