<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
        <section>
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <outcomes>
            <outcome> Explore increasing and decreasing functions, particularly in the context of concavity;</outcome>
            <outcome> Determine a function's concavity based on a table of values, a graph, or a description. </outcome>
          </outcomes>
          <p> In our mathematical adventures so far we have studied linear, quadratic, 
            and radical functions. The simplicity of these functions is useful when 
            introducing new concepts such as transformations, composition, and 
            inverse functions; but it is somewhat restrictive when we wish to 
            consider interesting real-world application problems.  </p>
          <p> For example, let's say that we were interested in modeling the 
            temperature of a hot cup of coffee since it was first poured. We cannot 
            write a formula for such a model yet, but perhaps <xref ref="exp-fig-motivatecool"/> depicts a reasonable
            approximation of the graph of it. Or perhaps
            we would like to model the growth in population of the world; again, 
            we can not write a formula for such a model at this stage, but you 
            might agree that <xref ref="exp-fig-motivatepop"/> is a likely candidate 
            for the graph of the model.  </p>
          <p> Clearly the functions depicted in <xref ref="exp-fig-motivate"/> belong to 
            a different class than those that we have considered so far. In fact, they 
            belong to the class known as <em>exponential</em> functions, the study of 
            which is a fascinating topic that encompasses many applications, and a lot 
            of interesting mathematical features. Prepare yourself for a colorful 
            and exciting
            journey that will take us through the landscape of some of the most useful 
            functions that we will ever encounter.  </p>
          <sidebyside xml:id="exp-fig-motivate">
              <figure width="40%" xml:id="exp-fig-motivatecool">
                <image>
                  <latex-image-code>
                  \begin{tikzpicture}
                  \begin{axis}[
                  framed,
                  xmin=-10,xmax=50,
                  ymin=-20,ymax=100,
                  xtick={-30}, ytick={-30},
                  minor xtick={10,20,...,50},
                  minor ytick={20,40,...,100},
                  xlabel={$t$},
                  grid=minor,
                  ]
                  \addplot+[->]expression[domain=0:50,samples=50]{40*exp(-x/10)+50};
                  \end{axis}
                  \end{tikzpicture}
                  </latex-image-code>
                </image>
                <caption></caption>
              </figure>
              <figure width="40%" xml:id="exp-fig-motivatepop">
                <image>
                  <latex-image-code>
                  \begin{tikzpicture}
                  \begin{axis}[
                  framed,
                  xmin=-10,xmax=50,
                  ymin=-20,ymax=100,
                  xtick={-30}, ytick={-30},
                  minor xtick={10,20,...,50},
                  minor ytick={20,40,...,100},
                  xlabel={$t$},
                  grid=minor,
                  ]
                  \addplot+[->]expression[domain=0:45,samples=50]{(1.1)^x+20};
                  \end{axis}
                  \end{tikzpicture}
                  </latex-image-code>
                </image>
                <caption></caption>
              </figure>
            <caption></caption>
          </sidebyside>
</section>
